# **Olafur Gudmundsson**

**Date of birth:** April 27, 1982 **Nationality:** Icelandic

Location:Kopavogur, IcelandPhone:+354 8992980Email:olafur.g@gmail.com

LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/olafurg">www.linkedin.com/in/olafurg</a>

**Skype:** olafur.g

## **Summary**

Experienced in management, information security management, quality assurance / software testing, software development practices and service operations.

Joined Betware (later NOVOMATIC Lottery Solutions, NLS) in January 2006 as a QA Specialist. Acted as a QA for several client and internal projects and gradually got more involved in information security matters, first as an internal auditor and later as a Security Manager. Participated in establishing a development hub in Belgrade, Serbia, as a QA Lead responsible for training, supporting and growing new development teams as well as holding the position of Security Manager for NLS globally. Between 2014-2019 I was the General Manager at NLS Serbia taking over the leadership role of the office.

At CCP Games leading the IT Operations and Information Security functions since April 2019.

## **Experience**

#### **IT Operations & Security Manager**

CCP Games | ccpgames.com

Leading the office IT, operations and information security functions.

General Manager Nov 2014 - Mar 2019

NOVOMATIC Lottery Solutions | novomaticls.com

Responsible for the daily operation and leadership of the NLS Serbia office.

### **Lead Quality Assurance Specialist**

Jun 2012 - Mar 2016

Apr 2019 - present

Betware (now NOVOMATIC Lottery Solutions) | novomaticls.com

Participated in establishing a development office in Serbia as a QA Lead. Responsible for recruiting, training and supporting new development teams. Initially 12 employees in two development teams growing up to around 80 employees in about 8 development teams, of which about 15 QAs.

- Participate in establishing a new development center in Belgrade.
- Coach new development teams, educate in agility, Scrum methodologies and support them in their work.
- Train and mentor new software QA Specialists.
- Participate in software development requirements analysis, testing, releasing, and support.
- Implement and maintain automated tests (checks) on the API and UI level.
- Write, maintain, review and follow test plans.
- Maintain test environments.
- Process improvements and look for opportunities to improve testing and other software development related processes.

Olafur Gudmundsson - CV

Security Manager Jan 2010 - Oct 2015

Betware (now NOVOMATIC Lottery Solutions) | novomaticls.com

Responsible for all information security matters. Implementing, maintaining, monitoring and operating the company's information security management system in accordance with the ISO 27001 and WLA-SCS standards and the company strategy.

- Define strategic direction of information security matters.
- Risk management (risk assessment, risk treatment).
- Security incident response, analysis and improvement implementations.
- Define, maintain and monitor effectiveness measurements.
- Business continuity management (business impact analysis, business continuity plans).
- Define, introduce, monitor and improve information security related policies and procedures.
- Ensure the information security management system, its policies and procedures are closely aligned with the core business processes of the company.
- Train employees in information security matters and organize awareness programs.

Internal Auditor May 2007 - Jan 2010

Betware (now NOVOMATIC Lottery Solutions) | novomaticls.com

Responsible for planning and conducting internal audits towards ISO 27001 and WLA-SCS as well as assisting with implementation and improvements related to the company's information security management system.

- Define internal auditing procedures and policies.
- Prepare internal audit plans.
- Perform and report on internal audits according to plans.
- Suggest and collaborate on appropriate improvements to business processes related to information security.

Split role, alongside the QA Specialist role (below).

#### **Quality Assurance Specialist**

Jan 2006 - Jun 2012

Betware (now NOVOMATIC Lottery Solutions) | novomaticls.com

Responsible for software testing efforts in cross-functional development teams in multiple projects building lottery solutions. Based on a Java back-end running on Linux servers, backed by Oracle/MSSQL databases with the front-end using modern technologies (HTML, CSS, JavaScript and various JS frameworks) and web services (REST, SOAP) to integrate with 3rd party services and providers.

- Participate in software development, requirements, testing, releasing and support.
- Write, maintain and follow test plans.
- Maintain test environments.
- Implement and maintain automated tests (checks) on the integration (API) and UI level.
- Process improvements and look for opportunities to improve testing processes.
- Mentor new software testers.
- Facilitate team project retrospectives.

#### **Education**

#### **B.Sc., Computer Science**

2009 - 2012

Reykjavik University, Aarhus University

Along with full time employment at Betware apart from one year at Aarhus University (2011-2012) as an exchange student during which I worked partly on security and QA duties at Betware.

Olafur Gudmundsson - CV

2/3

### **B.Sc. Industrial Engineering**

2002 - 2006

Reykjavik University

Majored in development, innovation and automation.

Initially at *Tækniskóli Íslands*, later renamed to *Tækniháskóli Íslands* and eventually merged with *Reykjavik University*. Graduated from RU.

### Courses and training

**The 4 essential roles of leadership.** Franklin Covey. Instructor Kristinn Tryggvi Gunnarsson. Four afternoon sessions over a 6 months period covering training about the 4 essential roles of leadership, strategy and strategy execution (4DX). <u>2019 (16 hours)</u>

**ISO/IEC 27001 Internal Auditor.** BSI Iceland. Instructor Geoff Dunn. Course about conducting internal audits for ISO 27001. Concluded with a certificate. 2009 (16 hrs)

**Agile Testing.** Betware internal course. Instructor Elizabeth Hendrickson. Course for QAs and other development related employees about testing efforts in an agile environment. Lectures and hands-on sessions. 2009 (2 days)

**Art of Agile.** Betware internal course. Instructor Jim Shore. Course for development related employees about Agile and XP (extreme programming). During the transition from traditional waterfall methods to an agile approach using Scrum and XP. 2008 (3 days)

**Internal audits for institutions and companies.** University of Iceland. Instructors Kjartan J Kárason and Einar Ragnar Sigurðsson. Course about conducting internal audits in general, not focusing on any specific standard. 2008 (10 hrs)

Introduction to Computer Networks for Non-Techies. Udemy, <a href="https://www.udemy.com/share/1000Hc/">https://www.udemy.com/share/1000Hc/</a>. 2019 (7 hours)

## **Specialities**

Agile methodologies, software testing and test management, information security management, risk management, business continuity, process improvements, establishing, supporting and growing development teams, leadership, management.

# Languages

**Icelandic:** Native

English: Professional proficiencyDanish: Limited working proficiencySerbian: Limited working proficiencyGerman: Elementary proficiency

Olafur Gudmundsson - CV